okay welcome back to migajina
no feeling all right
and we're gonna go to chapter 17
uh
which is
i don't know this chapter is weird
because you can understand it
so i i was thinking the guardian is
sitting there and it's like let me write
one chapter that they can understand
and uh
so i don't know you're probably gonna
get bored now
uh but here let's go to it okay now now
it's it's worthwhile to say
that you might ask yourself
why did he write a chapter that we could
understand now
you know after 16
understandable chapters why does it
suddenly give us an easy chapter
i think trying to guess why new
gardening
does stuff is like very interesting way
to spend a couple of hours
all right okay so here's the name of the
chapter
uh lei takashi jawa
and i i don't know if you notice tim for
example but he he changed the spelling
of talk
okay somebody changed the spelling
probably tony nama
and instead of saying an investigation
of
karma he says let's investigate karma
okay
it's interesting okay he made a verb
uh let's investigate karma okay so this
chapter is called the investigation of
karma
all right
here we go uh let's go to the first
uh doc do verse want to read time
good okay
yeah but it's it's
touching because he said
me myself
[Music]
where is he gonna go when the guardian
says me myself you're like
where are you going this
then he says donba domba
val but the verb
control yourself okay the verb for gamma
means to control yourself okay so
lex so nixon
well to control yourself
carefully
to control yourself
carefully okay
uh with and really it's champa
champa
love it's love chum sam means thoughts
of love
pando shen means to help others thoughts
of love where you want to help others
they now
all throughout these verses we go
dog
you can by the way you go to monster and
hear the kids memorizing
what's the difference
that's
that's dumb
it's powerful he says
what's
control yourself from hurting others be
nice to others
and love others they
don't say
say
that's dharma
yeah and tony llama adds a carpo there
couple
you have a couple shoot on
yeah
that's
that's that's
pure
that's pure dharma
the shawnee llama says that's dharma as
white as snow
picture
[Laughter]
okay that's dharma carpool cheney llama
says the guardian has said that's
dharma that's what dharma is loving
other people and not hurting them
but johnny llama says and that's as
white as snow okay
all right
now what happens if you do that kind of
thing
you get devil
you get results
and then okay
here's here's a hundred dollars
the tibetan translator
put okay christina
he put in the duel
he put winnie winnie when he wrote
fruits
or results
he used the ending which means the two
results
why
it's at the end of the third line if you
can guess
life
and in your future lives okay
for a hundred dollars how do the yoga
yoga sutra say that
in the first chapter of the yoga sutra
they say that exact same thing
experienced in this life and in the next
life seen in this life and seen in the
next level okay
all right
[Music]
anyway
the results of controlling yourself from
hurting others and from
thoughts of love towards others
is the sovereign
of jaibus
the two devils
in this life and your next life and the
future lies okay got it
there's nothing difficult about that
verse i don't know and the gods are
losing it
it's just a simple truth
then you're like suspicious you know
like well where's he going now
here we go
next verse
okay the great yogi
who's the great the ultimate young me
because sometimes he's called chang
the ultimate yogi
you could gotta use that in my
athleisure
the ultimate yogi means the buddha he
said
you can divide all karma lei
into simba
and samba
some
customs
[Music]
yeah thoughts on what they motivate
so thoughts and thought
thinking and thought
thinking and funked
okay thinking of time
that's a new verb saying
okay
means
uh intention and samba means what you
intended to do which means what you say
and what you do so he's covered how many
he's actually covered three kinds of
karma
simba
mental karma and then sampa
what you say and what you do and that's
all the kinds of karma they are okay
so the changsong chunk the great the
ultimate yogi he said
you can divide all karma into intending
to do something
and then the things you intended to do
okay
it's intentionally unintended
okay uh lady doki chitani now if you
want to divide those up chi chada right
here it is if you want to divide up
those kinds of karma
duma
there's billions
okay just forget it youngster dark means
you can find
described hundreds and hundreds and
hundreds of divisions okay basically
those two
intention and what you intended to say
or do
okay got it
uh
[Music]
let's do some sanskrit
okay
and
i thought it would be
nice to know the words for
intention
and what you intended to do or say okay
so here we go uh intention
or
what you thinking to do is called
chaitana okay
yeah the tibetan is
which is the definition of karma in
tibetan
karma is
thinking to do something
okay raw karma raw karma is intentional
okay
uh it comes from the root chi which
means to think
which literally means to shine and in
ancient times it was believed that
thinking illuminated the world
if you ever died the world would go dark
you see i mean that's why the world is
called loka
which means
lucid
same route roach also roach okay
to shine from within
so the world is illuminated by the mind
so the mind is called
chit which means which means
here it's called quite
it used to be
then it goes to
schwitt then it comes
then it becomes quite and then it
becomes white
okay
or wheat because that becomes white when
you grind it
so uh wheat means the white grain
okay so the mind
illuminates the world and that's
why
the mind is called the whitener
okay
and if you know russian i mean there are
many many roots
to consider she thought mr reed
i consider like that
okay no i read okay all right
now the opposite
okay
in tibetan what you thought
which means what you're doing and what
you're saying okay the funked thing
okay and that's just a simple
passive form right with the ya
that which you are thinking the torah
came into english as shun like
locomotion or action
okay all right mexican noun
cool we finished our just remember chit
means to think and it's tied up with
illumination
means shine
shine came from that okay all right
here we go
next verse so what's unusual about this
chapter so far
two verses in a row
we understood what the heck he's talking
about
and he doesn't seem to have brought up
emptiness
and i i assert that this is
the first verse he ever didn't bring it
up and he's got two in a row which is
really just i mean this is where
university scholars say somebody added
this chapter
which i don't think is true but um
anyway it's a little suspicious okay
here we go
universally miscarried
sam machining council
you guys can figure this out
what is simba it's yiki
karma of
the mind
what is samba
what's the thing you saw
it's yeah body and speech what you say
and what you do
three in a row
i'm definitely going up
okay i don't know what's the picture i
mean even the picture was boring
so i picked a picture from above
wait yeah i'm sorry no that's from the
last one that's uh thinking and thought
the balloon is thought okay i i'm
explaining to you
and here's talking and doing okay
which comes from thinking okay
all right let's go try to find a verse
which is challenging
oh here's one
uh
in the next two verses
he outlined seven types of karma okay he
promised us cheddar right what was that
he promised us
he promised us many categories of karma
well here they are
here's the easiest one
and it's it's intriguing
what nagarjuna thinks
is a division of karma because if
somebody asked me
what's the different kinds of karma i
would say the ten good deeds are there's
ten veterans right
and he goes off on this weird thing okay
which is so negative okay
here we go
well
not
okay that's easy talking okay not
talking
all right like mama is a typical tibetan
name which means uh
the power of speech
which means
physical action
it's interesting he calls it
moving
okay
moving your body
so how many kinds of karma so far two
okay two
uh
okay tim two hundred bucks
probably i'll be dharma
two divisions of
think of weird things in stanley's text
that have to do with karma
[Music]
yeah
one is what's the classic example when
you take a ball
when you get down on your knee and you
do this chicken posture thing
uh anyone can guess your motivation it's
my cup right you could be thinking about
lunch
but
so from the form someone can guess your
motivation
later according to the abu dharma you
have a
like a aura or a halo around you
which is your vows
influence uh stays and it's invisible
no one you can go to the bar
and uh
you can mike transfer here my goal is so
cute
yes you ruined my life and then the
second time i went there he had a beard
and i said what's going on you know
listen guess what we were on national tv
teaching dharma
and i said well yeah and he says i can't
go to the bar anymore
everybody's asking i had to grow a beard
so they wouldn't recognize it
so anyway why are we talking about that
uh you can't guess from the bearded guy
in the bar that he had the karmic aura
of having taught dharma on national tv
okay
okay those two are
which
if the first two are numbering
yeah then the next one's going to be
a non-communicating or now he's going to
talk about the aura
okay so so far we got two we got
speech
and physical movement okay
now we got namrik min okay
and then he calls it mi
you don't give up
and and johnny lama says that's the
guardian of shorthand for you don't give
up miguel
yeah
yeah so it implies you are
if you are miguel
you are
if you give up miguel you are
one yeah okay so why in the guardian
calls
good deeds
not giving up these
okay
it's because you don't give up bad deeds
okay he def he's describing good deeds
as not giving updates but that means not
giving up bad days which is good
days i'm sorry giving up
yeah okay
numbering
uh i'm sorry i screwed that up let's do
it again
means
yeah i'm sorry
yeah
you don't give up bad days i said it
right the first time
which is
a bad deed
no not giving up bad dates not giving a
bad
is a bad day that's all okay got it
sorry's right there
so the category number three
is not giving up bad days
which is bad deeds
okay but we already covered the
non-halo so this must be the
halo which means the afterglow you get
and tony lama says
from and by the way this is in the
abhidharma
when you joined a trade in ancient india
you had to take a a pledge
to follow that
occupation
and two famous pledges were butcher and
army and military
you know i will shoot people i will kill
people
that's called a domin dumba mimba what's
that
anti-vow
it's an antivirus i promise to follow my
father's trade
for the rest of my life my friend in
argentina
her husband is
it kills the animals in the
factory he's always depressed they don't
know why
uh
okay
so uh
anyway
uh so how many we got now uh we got good
we got
verbal karma
action karma which you can see
and then we got bad karma
hello
which is having made a promise to okay
and now we got uh
pong
where you do give up
bad days
okay the halo you get
when you do give up bad deeds and the
example of that halo is the one you get
after you take your when you're just
about to take your medicine buddha
initiation
you take your body supplements okay so
that halo everybody in this class if you
took the
negoginos bodhisattva ceremony
you have a halo around you forever
well uh yeah
for well some people say it stops when
you die but um not for bodhisattvas
so two kinds of halos
bad good halo
talking doing
that people can interpret
and then halos of bad deeds and good
deeds we got four how many he promised
us seven
he promised us seven
why in the garden wants to go this way
think about it
uh
number five you okay
yeah non-communicating is three and four
and communicating is one and two
okay cool we didn't get to the mental
ones now
yeah
long chilly
okay uh
oh shenda
apply that to all the others apply that
to all the others and he means by that
good or bad
okay good or bad when i'm definite
dividing things into
good or bad you know
keep doing that with the rest of them
okay
[Music]
this is interesting uh material
good deeds relating to the dharma
material good deeds relating to the
dharma making a donation to say books
with the gold club or making a donation
to build a stupa
for medicine buddha and that has a
special name
it's very interesting um
like i spent 30 years uh
fixing the temple in new jersey the
mongolian monastery i did i did i
rebuilt many of the houses and stuff
like that
and i'm still getting interested
on the as long as some monk is sitting
in that house i'm getting interest
karmic interest that's called zeleto
so what he's number five
it's the guardian of things seems
important
to isolate
this special karma you get
from physical
donations contributions to the dharma
which will outlive you
or which will outlive your current
participation after you quit the gold
club
if the gold club saved a lot of books
then every time geshe-la uses that book
in the class
you're still getting karmic interest
it's cool now for some reason the
guardian thinks it's important to
separate that one out
okay
so that could be a whole
conversation in a in a study group or
something okay
all right
which means that the medicine with a
stupid project and saving the books
project
are interesting projects
because you keep getting interest out of
them even if you quit the group
you still get the interest all right all
right cool i'm still getting interest
from all the
like i built a water system in ceremony
so every time some monk takes a drink
i'm like getting more karma
all right uh
sun and mayan soda
the same applies to the opposite and
tony llama says building a facility for
killing cows
would be an example if you build it and
then they keep killing cows there
you keep getting karmic interest okay
that's six we've done six what's number
seven gonna be uh simba
the pre-intent
okay like what was your intention before
you did those six
what were you hoping would be
accomplished good or bad okay but he
puts them together so that's seven so we
don't get an equal number because he
puts them together
okay
somebody super accepts that
okay who the buddha
okay those are the divisions to what he
first described as only two semba and
samba
and
okay now now you've got seven any
difficult verse yet
no i think he's gonna kick us in the
butt i think something's coming i'm just
guessing
okay there's a picture trying to find a
picture of these seven
good luck uh i was thinking you know
good and bad commerce
anyway let's skip on
uh
me to paddle now finally
why did he set us up
with this come with this
calm
understandable
discussion of karma because he was
coming this was coming
okay
now he's like here's the guardian
wow so we did all these kinds of karma
well what happens after that
what do you think happens after that you
know
where does the karma stay until it
ripens
you know now he's he was setting us up
for three verses right
five verses
he was setting us up
and now he asks this innocent question
oh where does the karma stay
until it ripens you know
and then he's like
two possibilities
uh
if it stays somewhere
inert
until it comes out
well then it's stuck it's unchanging
during that period
it has to replicate itself
as the same it has to clone itself
from year to year until it ripens right
so that's unchanging that's
and that's impossible for a functional
thing
no functional entity in the universe
cannot change
even for one minute forget 12 lifetimes
or something not possible okay so
can we here's the garden
can we cancel the first possibility
that it sits there in your brain not
changing
yeah it has to change if it's a
functional thing it changes why
because it's pushed by a cause and that
energy starts to
slow down okay
as it goes through time okay now
oh gesture your thing you're staying the
longer a karma stays in your mind the
less strong it gets
okay well here's the other chance choice
if you say it's not unchanging
then it stops and we don't have to
experience the result of the government
yay
okay does it
does it replicate or does it stop it
can't replicate because then it would
stay the same and it's a functional
thing
and it can't stop or else all the laws
of karma would be broken if it stops all
the laws of cover would be broken you
could do whatever you want
and hope that the karma stops before it
opens
okay
did you ever think about it
okay somebody tell me why the next
picture is relevant
did you ever apply for a job in new york
or l.a
i'm not asking my friend
you spent hours in waiting rooms right
were you the same person who went into
the waiting room
i mean to me your karma is like goes to
the waiting room and then they finally
someone says okay i'll interview you you
know what they always say and they say
oh it's five o'clock can you come back
tomorrow you say i've been here since
three o'clock
that's called
applying for a job in new york early
right
okay you know
all right
next birth
by the way the final two verses of what
i chose for this class
and we'll continue in the next class
because this is a long chapter
uh two lower schools come and try to
explain the question
okay so i assume some bigger school's
gonna come later i don't know i didn't
read ahead
but uh
here's the here's the answer of the
dodeca
the
sutra school second school
and
what they call it kache
kache which means kashmiris
the guys from kashmir
which means an abhidharma school that
used to hang out in northern india
later
that area became muslim
and now the the tibetan word for muslim
is kashmiri
same word okay like punjab right
okay
here we go
may not be on june
okay
uh first you have the seed by the way
who's this lower buddhists okay well
first you have it they're answering the
gospel
first you have the suit okay
uh
new colossal gym canyon
and then it opens
and there's a flow
sorry
before it opens
first you have the seed
and then something comes out which is a
flow
here's the seed the flow come breaks out
and then it ripens
so no problem
it's not that the seed is repeating
itself which would be unchanging which
is impossible the seed produces
something right away it's called
the flow
of the karma here's the seed
karma opens comes out
wait
[Music]
okay and that's the ripening of the
karma
so no problem
does the seed ripen into the karma
runway no it flows
and then what happens at the end of the
flow it opens into the result
got it
therefore no problem
it's still changing because it's flowing
but the the karmic result hasn't opened
yet
got it no problem
seed flow result
got it
that's the lower buddhist school
uh de la juveni
uh
and then comes the result okay maina
deon jumingir
the result could not have happened
without the seed first
therefore the result is connected to the
seed if the seed had never happened the
result at the end of the flow never
would have come out therefore the seed
is causing the result but via
a flow
so they get out of the question
that the seed didn't cost me some the
seed came before the result
it did cost the result it just took a
while and it was flowing okay that's
their thing
conscious of the negan down
how does that work again
there's a solvent there's a seed
then there's a flow gin
and then gin laid debu
then the flow turns into the result okay
and because
the seed must predate the result okay
we avoid your two extremes
which is another version of the two
husbands extremes which is a more simple
version of the two husbands extremes
which means
does the seed ever stop
or does the seed go on unchanging both
of those are extremes why
if the seeds shut down before the result
came out
they're never been resolved if the seed
kept going on the same way until the
result came out
that would be unchanging and that's not
possible for a functional thing so just
it's just the flow man
stay with the flow
[Music]
okay
who is that lower school all right
uh
we got
by the way then the guys was like the
guys you know everybody's looking at
this lower buddhist guy's like
like this you know
huh
and they say let's explain let us
explain further
which usually means digging a deeper
hole for themselves
you know the guys was like what and then
like
the next two verses is the next two
verses is their clarification
of their position okay by the way if you
don't have tony llama you don't know
that
it sounds like nagarjuna okay
and then that turns into the result
the mind
the mind begets a mental flow and then
the mental flow turns into the result
okay three steps
delay debu
he uses instrumental bus
boom which means therefore okay that the
other guy is drawing a conclusion
because there's a mind and because then
the flow of the mind and then the result
comes back therefore
semtashi
means
it's a it's a idiomatic expression which
means uh
forget it without the mind you've got to
have something sheik means forget it if
there's no mind there has to be money
why i just told you mind flow result
don't tell me you can't have a mind at
the beginning of that
without that nothing semtoshi means you
can't dump the mind you gotta have the
mind there it it tashik means
you know what the hell
without the mind okay
if the mind wasn't there
jung mangir the whole process would
never happen it has to start with mind
then mind flows
okay if you say the flow of the mind is
not part of the process then how could
you have a karma if you didn't have any
thinking
okay
he's like nikon what do you call it
fabricating
logical
prevent
you're switching
terms
anyway it has to start with the mind why
karma starts with the mind are you
telling me there's no mind no no no this
is mine why mine is the base of karma
okay so it's flowing what do you have
problem with that
that's all you say
okay you never could have had a karmic
result without in mind anyway so don't
tell me my theory is wrong
that there's a flow because the flow
happens to be the flow of the mind which
you agree has to be there at the
beginning
got it
okay
contour stamina
given a day with ginger
i just told you
the flow comes from the mind and then
the mind keeps flowing and then at the
end of the flow you get a devil you get
a result
and because
[Music]
the planting of the karma in the mind
has to pre-date the result
i avoid your problems the two problems
that you suggested what were the two
problems we suggested number one that
the karmic seed
would would keep replicating itself
unchangedly
or that it would
just
what do you call that
truncate
okay
got it that's a perfect word actually
write that down
all right uh we finished uh that first
half of that chapter
we will continue with deep dive class
number 13 in the next let's let's
summarize
uh nagarjuna set us up
with some understandable stuff
at the beginning right
what is karma thinking
and then the the actions motivated by
thinking
and speech and then he got into seven
different kinds which included
uh the halo star
you know and
and
emphasized had a on
had and noticeable
bias
towards
physical dharma actions
supporting physical like like the input
project okay
and then he went on to discuss whether
or not
what
how does the
seed stay in the mind if it doesn't
change there's a problem if it does stop
there's a problem okay
and and then we had an attempted
explanation by some guys who keep
talking about some kind of floating
that connects the result to the original
seed without the seed changing or
stopping
cool
all right see you next class